本片涉及圣经内容的名词 段落 均参照和合本翻译
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调&校对: 影子
翻译: 奥利奥 飘飘行天下 鸟生鱼汤 舒大卷子 波特妹子
公元: 圣经续 第一季第1集
真理?
Truth?
何为真理?
What is truth?
这里好些人看见你召唤魔鬼帮人疗伤
Many here have seen you employ demons to heal
并称之为神的工作!
and call it the work of God!
好些人听见你说要毁掉神殿
Many heard you say you would destroy the temple
三天后再重新建一个
and in three days build another.
有人在犹太公会前作证
Some testified here before the Sanhedrin
告你说过这些
that you said this.
你有何说法?
How do you respond?
你拒绝回答吗?
Are you going to refuse to answer?
你是不是弥赛亚?
Are you or are you not the Messiah?
我是
I am.
很快你们就要看见人子
And soon you will see the son of man
坐在神的右手边
sitting at the right hand of God.
你胆敢直呼他的尊名?!
How dare you speak his name?!
他犯了亵渎神明之罪
The charge is blasphemy.
应当处死!
He deserves to die!
犹大!
Judas!
你
You.
你是他的同伙!
You're one of his men!
不 我... 我不是
No. I... I'm not.
这个人是拿撒勒人的同伙!
This man is one of the Nazarene's men!
我... 我不认识他 你们认错人了!
I... I don't know him. You're mistaken!
这个人和"神的儿子"是一伙的!
This man walks with this "son of God"!
我不是! 我不认识他!
I do not! I don't know him!
我没见过他!
I've never seen him before!
带走他
Take him away.
巡抚
Governor.
那个拿撒勒人的名望助长了
The Nazarene's popularity has strengthened
犹太教狂热信徒的造反之心
the zealots' resolve to rise against us.
审判他可能会引发叛乱
His trial could trigger rebellion.
一个犹太人的话怎能对抗整个罗马的势力?
The word of one Jew against the might of Rome?
我不这么认为 马略
I don't think so, Marius.
耶路撒冷
不要!
Don't!
释放他!
Release him!
放了他!
Let him go!
你是犹太人的王吗?
Are you the king of the Jews?
我的国不属这世界
My kingdom is not of this world.
那么你是王吗?
So you are a king, then?
你说我是王
You say that I am.
我为此而生 也为此来到世间
I was born and came into this world
特为给真理作见证
to testify to the truth.
凡属真理的人 就听我的话
Everyone on the side of the truth listens to me.
真理?
Truth?
何为真理?
What is truth?
我查不出他有什么罪来
I find no basis for a charge against him.
钉他十字架!
Crucify him!
带走他...
Take him...
并钉他十字架!
and crucify him.
钉他十字架!
Crucify him!
让开!
Out of the way!
钉进去
Nail them in.
逾越节
看他们倾其所有地进贡
See how they come in their hundreds of thousands
来祈求神的庇护
to keep themselves in God's favor.
这神殿的确是整个庆典中
It is undeniable that the temple is a great focal point
人们的焦点 神父
for their celebrations, father.
但他们的生活得以蒸蒸日上
However, they thrive in their daily lives
全靠大祭司的领导
due to the leadership of the high priest.
你保护了我们的祭祀礼仪
You have protected our sacrificial rites admirably
使之不随拿撒勒人的私念而被废除
against the Nazarene's desire to sweep them away.
我唯一的遗憾是让巡抚参与进来了
My one regret is that you involved the Governor.
动用罗马法的全部条令很有必要
It was necessary to call upon the full force of Roman law.
把那拿撒勒人钉上十字架警告了
The Nazarene's crucifixion sends a message
所有想毁掉我们辛苦支撑起的信仰的人
to all who might challenge what we labor so hard to uphold.
你做得很对
You did the right thing.
这还有待定论
That is open to question.
久而久之 会有更多的人被那个拿撒勒人
Day by day, more and more people were being seduced
通俗的说教所迷惑
by the Nazarene's simplistic homilies.
他必须被揭发
He had to be exposed.
并如此残忍地处决?
And so brutally executed?
我丈夫所做的决定
My husband took a decision
是所有大祭司都会做的决定
any high priest would have taken.
虽然我在管事的时候
Though my methods may have differed
做法会不同
during my time in office,
但最终目标还是一致的
I would have pursued the same objective.
这是在滥杀无辜
It was the needless death of a harmless soul.
"无辜"?
"Harmless"?
他威胁了我们所代表的一切
He threatened everything we represent
以及人们的信仰
and these people believe in.
约瑟 为了神的子民
The life of one man is as nothing, Joseph,
一条人命不足为惜
for the sake of God's nation.
该亚法...
Caiaphas...
够了
Ah, enough.
晚餐时再见吧
We shall see you at supper.
约瑟夫和他的崇高道德
Joseph and his lofty morals.
凌驾于公共事务的污垢之上
Floating above the daily grime of public affairs.
空话易说
Well, words come cheap.
不付诸实际行动
Without actions to test them,
他就是纸上谈兵
his opinions are fruitless.
同享这盛宴吧 我们饿坏了
Share this feast. We're hungry.
那个拿撒勒人自称
Is it correct the Nazarene alleged
能起死回生 是吗?
he would rise from death?
他那是在胡说八道
One of his many outrageous claims
并对预言无理篡改
and crude manipulations of prophecy.
那就确保他迅速死去
Then ensure he dies swiftly
别让他有机会实施最后的骗术
before he has the chance to perform a final deception.
赶在天黑前 该亚法
Before the first star, Caiaphas.
别让那肮脏之景
Before the very sight of the rogue
玷污了我们的庆典
is allowed to pollute our celebrations.
耶和华阿 我要求告你
To you Lord, I call.
我的磐石阿
You are my rock.
不要向我缄默 倘若你向我闭口
Do not turn a deaf ear to me, for if you remain silent,
我就如将死的人一样
I shall be like those who go down to the pit.
我呼求你
Hear my cry for mercy.
向你至圣所举手的时候
I call for your help
求你垂听我恳求的声音
as I lift my hands to your most holy place.
主啊?
My God?
为什么离弃我?
Why have you forsaken me?
报告两件事 巡抚
Two items, Governor.
大祭司该亚法要求尽快处决
A request to expedite the death of the Nazarene
那个拿撒勒人
from high priest Caiaphas
另有人请求在那个拿撒勒人死后取走他的尸体
and a petition to repossess the Nazarene's body upon death.
谁请求取走尸体?
Who requests the body?
一位犹太长老
A Jewish elder
他因为犹太公会对那个拿撒勒人的迫害而倍感烦恼
troubled by the Sanhedrin's persecution of the Nazarene.
他的姓名?
His name?
来自亚利马太的约瑟
Joseph of Arimathea.
俱准了
Grant each request.
让他们继续互相争吵
Keeping them at each other's throats
好叫他们不要来摆布我们
prevents them from wrapping their fingers around ours.
叫哥尼流去结束那个拿撒勒人的痛苦吧
And have Cornelius put the Nazarene out of his misery.
你喜欢这幅奇观吗?
Are you enjoying the spectacle?
奇观?
Spectacle?
你就是如此看待
Is that how you regard
拿撒勒人被钉上十字架这事的吗?
the crucifixion of the Nazarene?
在罗马的土地上宣称为王的人
Any man who claims to be king in a Roman province
便犯了叛国罪
is committing treason
必须承受这后果
and must suffer the consequences.
在我的梦里他并不如王一般行事
He does not behave as a king in my dreams.
这领地的运转可不能由
The running of the province can hardly be determined
巡抚夫人的梦来决定
by the dreams of the Governor's wife.
神会在我们沉眠时找到我们
The gods find us in our sleep.
他们的讯息很明确
Their message was clear.
那个拿撒勒人是个好人
The Nazarene is a good man.
谦卑 清心
Humble. Pure of heart.
那个人对现状而言是个危险
The man was a danger to the status quo.
我们在犹太的驻军规模并不大 克劳迪娅
Our Garrison in Judea is not large, Claudia.
你会后悔参与了他的死亡
You'll live to regret your hand in his death.
我采纳了建议
I took advice.
我权衡了利弊
I weighed it up.
我照章办事
I acted accordingly.
你采纳的建议来自那些
Advice from men
惧怕他的风头会盖过自己的人
who feared his popularity would eclipse their own.
他宣称自己是他们的弥赛亚
He claimed to be their Messiah.
让人忍无可忍
It was intolerable.
最坏情况不过是他疯了!
At worst, he's mad!
难道这足以...
Is that reason enough...
克劳迪娅
Claudia.
所有犹太牧师都与我作对
It's tiresome enough
已经让我够烦了
having every Jewish priest on my back.
我可不希望我的夫人也加入他们的行列
I don't expect my own wife to join them,
而且没错 即便他是疯子
and, yes, even if he were mad,
我们也必须把他钉起来好除灭他这使者
we should nail him up to destroy the messenger
也警告人民不能听信他的传道!
and to warn the people against his message!
杀了他并不会是他的终结
Killing him won't be the end of him.
通常是如此 亲爱的
It usually is, my darling.
成... 成了...
I... it is... finished.
自己逃命吧!
Save yourselves!
跟我来!
Come with me!
别挡着我!
Out of my way!
走这里!
This way!
这是他的母亲
This is his mother.
那又如何?
So?
就别验了 你能看出他已经死了
Spare her this. You can see he's dead.
那得由我说了算
I'll be the judge of that.
实在不必如此
There's no need for this.
求你了
Please.
上头的命令是要确保他死了
The order is to make sure.
来者何人
Identify yourself.
我有权拥有
I have permission to take possession
那个拿撒勒人的尸体
of the Nazarene's body.
谁的许可?
On whose authority?
巡抚的
The Governor's.
若您愿意
If you will allow,
我愿贡献出我自己的墓地
I would like to offer my own tomb
作为您儿子的安息之地
as your son's final place of rest.
他在那会得享安宁
He'll be at peace there.
我已做下最糟糕的事...
I've done the most terrible thing...
这行为不可饶恕
for which there can be no forgiveness.
我卖了无辜之人的血!
I've betrayed innocent blood!
她累坏了
She's exhausted.
她在等待
She's waiting.
她是真的坚信不疑
Does she really believe it,
还是悲痛让她宁愿相信一个虚无缥缈的希望?
or is it what her grief wills her to believe?
我觉得她真的坚信他会从死里复活
I think she truly believes he will rise from death.
你信吗?
Do you?
我明晚再告诉你们剩下的故事
And I'll tell you the rest of the story tomorrow night.
晚安 去吧 上床去
Good night. Come, off to bed.
晚安
Good night.
喝点东西
Drink something.
有生之年我从不敢想象
In my lifetime, I could never have imagined
神的殿堂竟会遭受如此损毁
such an assault on the house of God.
我的心都碎了
My heart breaks.
我们可以修复它
We can restore it.
又不是因为你的缘故
It was not of your making.
没人死亡已经是奇迹
Miraculous that no one was killed.
啊
Ah.
我们还以为你不会来了
We thought you weren't coming.
抱歉
Apologies.
请进 请进
Come in. Come in.
我们有事耽搁了
We were waylaid.
怎么了?
Why?
我安葬了一个可怜的灵魂
I was laying a poor soul to rest.
亲戚吗?
A relative?
被钉上十字架的那个拿撒勒人
The crucified Nazarene.
你再说一遍?
I beg your pardon?
他死后理应得到尊重
He deserved greater respect in death
而不该再像生前所承受的那样
than he'd ever been afforded in life.
约瑟啊 他的追随者称他为拉比
Because his followers named him Rabbi, Joseph,
不代表他就是的
doesn't mean he was one.
拿撒勒人为那些
The Nazarene gave succor
与罗马对抗的人提供帮助
to those would take up arms against Rome.
这将成为灾难
Which would have been a disaster,
罗马会因此而招兵买马
prompting Rome to unleash reinforcements
最后导致犹太人的鲜血
that would turn the Mediterranean red
染红整个地中海
with Jewish blood.
我不认为会有这样的威胁
I don't agree he posed the threat you believe.
这就是你永远不会成为大祭司的原因
Which is why you will never become the high priest.
犹太人民忍受了
The Jewish people have survived
太多帝国的暴虐统治
the tyranny of many empires
他们务实又忍让
with pragmatism and compromise.
谨慎地前行
With careful helmsmanship,
他们会比罗马帝国存活地更为长久
it will outlast the Roman occupation.
也不至于要罗马帝国把犹太人钉死在十字架上
Not by asking Rome to crucify Jews, it won't.
我能问一下那个拿撒勒人被埋葬在哪里吗?
May I ask where the Nazarene was buried?
在我的墓地
In my tomb.
"人还使他与恶人同埋
"And he made his grave with the wicked
谁知死的时候与财主同葬"
and his tomb with the rich."
你很熟悉以赛亚的预言吗?
You are familiar with Isaiah's prophecy?
我并不盲从于预言 而是尊重
I wasn't compelled by prophecy, but decency.
我很难相信
I find this hard to believe.
就在我们试图
At the very hour we sought
熄灭这个危险的火苗时
to extinguish this dangerous flame,
你却又亲手把它点燃!
you take it upon yourself to re-ignite it!
我不是有意为之
I had no intention other than
只是想体面地结束这一肮脏的事件
to bring this sordid episode to a dignified conclusion.
但对那些脆弱的心灵来说
But to the weak of mind,
你就是在让以赛亚的预言成真!
you create the appearance of fulfilling Isaiah!
你难道看不出其中的问题吗?
Do you not understand the issue here?
他究竟犯了什么罪?
What precisely was his crime?
是因为他宣扬待人
To preach that we should treat each other
要以待己之道吗?
as we ourselves would wish to be treated?
他被处决是因为反复亵渎神明
He was killed for the repeated blasphemy
声称自己是弥赛亚
of claiming to be the Messiah.
- 如果他是呢?  - 那他也已经不是了
- And if he was?  - Then he is no more.
罗马并未对犹大省严加管制
Rome holds Judea loose in its hand
只是因为犹太公会可以管理自己的人民
only as long as the Sanhedrin is able to manage its people.
除了和平与爱
In addition to peace and love,
拿撒勒人煽动人们
the Nazarene preached insurrection
反抗所有当权者
against all authority.
我不同意
I disagree.
你竟如此傲慢!
Such arrogance!
约瑟 你终会明白
But you will see, Joseph.
记着我的话 无论是否在你的墓地里
You have my word, in or out of your tomb,
拿撒勒人的教义都将随其尸体一起腐烂
the Nazarene's doctrine will decompose with his corpse.
彼得!
Peter!
你怎么了?
What happened to you?
我被认出来了
I was recognized.
我努力逃了出来
I managed to get away.
其他人在这里吗?
The others are here?
没有 玛利亚确信
No. Mary is convinced
当权者会追捕我们
the authorities will be hunting us down.
你应该马上离开
You should leave immediately.
自己一个人? 不
Without them? No.
你去了哪里 彼得?
Where were you, Peter?
他死了吗?
Is he dead?
我亲手安葬了他
I laid him to rest myself.
那就结束了
Then it's over.
耶稣曾预言犹大会向公会揭发自己
Jesus foretold that Judas would betray him to the Sanhedrin.
他确实那样做了
And he did.
他也曾预言你会说不认识他
He also foretold that you would deny him.
告诉我们你没那么说
Tell us you didn't.
我不能撒谎
I can't lie.
在审判的时候
There was a trial.
那些暴徒恨不得吸干他的血 然后...
The mob was baying for his blood, and...
我被认出来了
I was recognized.
如果他都死了 还有什么分别呢?
What difference does any of this now make if he's dead?
我们虚度了生命中最后的三年
The last three years of our lives for nothing.
他的母亲相信他会重生
His mother believes he will rise.
如果是真的 我宁愿失去这只手!
I would give this arm to believe the same!
从没想过你会是个懦夫
I never had you for a coward.
从来没有
Never.
退后! 退后!
Back! Back up!
让他走开
Send him away.
德鲁苏斯
Drusus.
巡抚
Governor.
神殿大祭司求见
The high priest of the temple.
他不能等我用完餐吗?
Can't it wait until after I've eaten?
不 恐怕不行
No, I'm afraid it can't.
这件事有点紧急
This is a matter of some urgency.
该亚法 紧急似乎是你的常态
"Urgent" appears to be your default state of mind, Caiaphas.
因为我们生活在动荡的时代 巡抚
We live in turbulent times, Governor.
我有一个请求
I have a request.
又来一个?
Another one?
千万别告诉我又是关于拿撒勒人的
Please tell me it doesn't concern the Nazarene.
我对您迄今为止代表我们所做出的
I'm certainly grateful for the decisive manner
果断决定深表感激
in which you've acted on our behalf so far.
迄今为止?
"So far"?
你想要得寸进尺
You seek more from me on this.
恐怕是的
I'm afraid so.
你想把他钉死在十字架上 我已经钉死他了
You wanted him crucified, I had him crucified.
还有什么必须做的吗?
What more is necessary?
这个无名小卒又有什么事扰你不得安宁了?
What is it about this nobody that so disturbs you?
如您所知 他的尸体被葬在了
As you know, his corpse has been placed
一位长老的墓地中
in the tomb of an elder.
"如您所知"是什么意思?
What do you mean, "as you know"?
是真的吗?
Is this true?
是有人请愿
A petition was made.
您一定要知道这会导致怎样的冲突
You must have known the friction it would cause.
从没想过这个问题
It never crossed my mind.
与他过去的恶行一样
In keeping with his practice,
拿撒勒人歪曲了先人们
the Nazarene distorted ancient prophecies
关于弥赛亚复活的预言
relating to the rise of our Messiah
并且散播谣言 声称在他死去三天之后
and spread rumor that he would rise from his own death
他将复活
after three days.
该亚法 钉死在十字架上是不会复活的
Roman crucifixion really doesn't allow for that, Caiaphas.
然而 允许他的尸体被埋葬
Nevertheless, by allowing his body to be entombed
而不是让野兽吃掉
and not consumed by wild beasts,
你给了他的门徒机会
you've granted an opportunity to his followers
去制造耶稣复活的假象
to enact the appearance of resurrection.
我们都明白 在耶路撒冷 一个假象
And as we know, in Jerusalem, the appearance of a thing
和事物本身同样有说服力
is often as potent as the thing itself.
你相信门徒们会在三天后侵入墓地?
You believe they will raid the tomb after three days?
这是操纵事件最简单的方法
It'd be the simplest way to manipulate events.
那就确保尸体不会被盗走
Then ensure it isn't removed.
让神殿的护卫把守在外面
Post temple guards outside.
恐怕我的人并阻止不了
I fear my men would pose no deterrent
那帮狂徒
to a band of fanatics.
你希望我浪费罗马士兵
You want me to waste Roman soldiers
去看守一个犹太人的墓地?
guarding a Jewish hole?
还要在墓上贴上罗马封条
And place a Roman seal across the tomb.
非法入侵将会被处以死刑
Its unlawful breaking carries the death penalty.
你要求的太多了
You ask too much.
如果您没有允许埋葬他
Had you not granted permission to entomb him,
局势就不会像现在这样
this situation would not have arisen.
不管他躺在哪里 他目前对于
Where he lies, he currently remains a threat
公会和罗马都仍是威胁
both to the Sanhedrin and to Rome.
一个人?
One man?
你低估了罗马最高领主的能力
You underestimate the might of your Roman overlords.
但如果这样做可以结束掉这一切
But if it will finally bring an end to this,
我会派遣一小队士兵去看守墓地
I will post a small guard outside the tomb.
感激不尽
I cannot thank you enough.
终于 我们有达成一致的事情了
At last, something we can agree upon.
你怎么没告诉我?
Why didn't you tell me?
我不需要向你或是任何人说明我的决定
I don't have to account for my decisions to you or anyone else.
不要张望 马太
Don't look now, Matthew,
我觉得我们可能被发现了
but I think we may have been spotted.
要回头吗?
Do you want to go back?
如果回头 就证实了他们的怀疑
If we do, we confirm their suspicions.
继续走
Just keep moving forward.
嘿! 你们!
Hey! You!
跑!
Run!
你喊我就杀了你 明白吗?
Shout out and you're dead, understood?
这边! 继续找!
This way! Keep looking!
罗马士兵为什么在追你们?
Why were you running from the Romans?
在我们杀死你们之前
You have one chance to speak the truth
你有一次机会说出真相
before we leave your corpses here.
我们是拿撒勒的耶稣的门徒
We're disciples of Jesus of Nazareth.
继续说
Go on.
在他被捕之后 我们逃出城去了
We fled the city after he was captured.
那你们为什么现在要回这个犹大省
Then why come back to where there are more Roman soldiers
罗马士兵最多的地方?
than anywhere else in Judea?
为了找我们的兄弟
To find our brothers.
他像凡人一样流血
Well, he bled like a man.
把它弄走
Remove it.
但要拆掉
But break it up.
我认识这个人
I recognize this man.
波阿斯
Boaz.
你认识这个狂热分子?
You know this zealot?
我们小时候在加利利一起玩耍的
We played together in Galilee as children.
很久以前的事了 彼得
An age away, Peter.
时间改变了我们
The times reshape us all.
是的
They do.
你是耶稣的门徒?
You are disciples of the Nazarene?
我们是
We are.
你们的领导者有很多追随者
Your leader had a great following on the streets.
当权者密谋并杀害了他
The authorities colluded and murdered him.
加入我们 成为一股真正能对抗他们的力量
Join us and become a real force to be reckoned with.
和罗马人开战?
Fighting the Romans?
不计代价将他们赶出我们的土地
Whatever it takes to drive them off our land.
生于剑 死于刀
Live by the sword, and you die by the sword.
那总好过像被拴住的狗一样
Better that than like a dog on a leash.
你的老师宣扬爱
Your master preached love.
我将拼死宣扬自由
I shall die preaching freedom.
加入我们!
Join us!
我们是渔夫 不是战士
We are fishermen, not fighters.
他们不会善罢甘休的
They won't stop with him.
你知道的吧?
You do know that?
一旦他们认识到
Once the Romans realize
你们的启示仍是威胁
your message remains a threat,
他们会将你们连根拔除
they will root you out.
当他们杀光所有门徒
And when they've killed each of you,
就会一个接一个的清除他的思想
they will snuff out his ideas one by one
直到你们好像从来没有存在过一样
until it will be as if you never existed.
加入我们
Join us.
我不能
I cannot.
我们在等什么?
What are we waiting for?
我想出来的可以让你不再
The means by which I intend to put an end
不停地为这个耶稣啜泣的办法
to your incessant mewling about this Jesus.
我没有保持观点的权利吗?
Am I not entitled to an opinion?
你有的
You are.
但妄想不是一种观点 克劳迪娅
But obsession is not opinion, Claudia,
而且反常的妄想需要彻底的根治
and unhealthy obsession requires radical treatment,
根治的办法我想现在也该到了
which I believe is arriving now.
哥尼流 我有点事只有你可以处理
Cornelius, I have a certain matter only you can clear up.
如果我可以的话 愿意效劳
If I can, of course.
我想从你这里了解一件事情
I need to know one thing from you.
当他被放到坟墓里的时候
When he was placed inside his tomb,
你确定拿撒勒人已经死了吗?
are you certain the Nazarene was dead?
大人 当我被命令去做事 我就去做
Sir, when I'm instructed to do a job, I do it.
我当时被命令确保
I was instructed to ensure
拿撒勒人死在十字架上
the death of the Nazarene on the cross,
我那时就是这么做的
and that's what I did.
他在你面前断气了?
He expired before you?
比这还好
Better than that.
他是因为我才断的气
He expired because of me.
你验过尸体了吗?
And you performed the proofs of death?
我让朗基奴斯拿枪
I instructed Longinus to insert his spear
扎拿撒勒人的肋旁
hard between the Nazarene's ribs.
他死了?
And he was dead?
扎进去之前和之后都死了
Before and after the spear.
所以说 对于任何怀有
So, to anyone who might entertain
他可能没死的妄想的人
the notion that he might not be dead,
认为拿撒勒人在经受了你方才所说的一切后
that the Nazarene might actually somehow have remained alive
还奇迹般的活着的人
after all of what you've just described,
你会怎么说?
you would say what?
我会说他们不是疯子就是傻瓜
I would say they were either mad or a fool.
谢谢 哥尼流
Thank you, Cornelius.
你可以退下了
You may go.
别疑神疑鬼说无稽之谈了 克劳迪娅
Enough of your dreams and nonsense, Claudia.
那个拿撒勒人也不过是血肉之躯
The Nazarene was only ever flesh and blood.
而他的血肉
And we have butchered the former
已被我们洒在这个城市
and spilled the latter all over the city.
但如果你再梦到他
But if you should dream of him again,
确保他真的化成肉身
be sure he proves his true identity
证明自己的身份
by his real incarnation.
不是什么花言巧语的预言
Not as a handsome prophet with charisma,
而是站在地上的腐烂肉体
but as a rotting pile of meat on the floor.
我只是不确定
I'm just questioning
现在离开耶路撒冷
whether leaving Jerusalem at this moment in time
是正确的抉择
is the right course of action.
保住自己的命
How can saving our lives
怎么可能不是正确的选择?
not be the right course of action?!
我们不一定能走到城墙
There's no guarantee we'll make it to the city wall.
但他们也不一定在追杀我们
But there's no guarantee they're actually coming after us.
大祭司和彼拉多形影不离
The high priest walks hand-in-hand with Pilate!
他们已经杀了我们的领导者
They killed our leader.
我们有何能继续危害他们的权威?!
How do we continue to pose a threat to their authority?!
五千人走到遥远的山坡上
5,000 people on a remote hillside
只为听他布道...
just to hear him preach...
那是他 不是我们
That was him, not us.
你们难道已经忘了他的预言?
Have you forgotten his prophecy already?
你忘了吗 彼得?
Have you forgotten, Peter?
第三日时 他保证会起死复生
On the third day, he promises to rise from death.
您需要休息
You need to rest.
他们怎么这么快就忘了?
Have they forgotten so quickly?
他们不能等等吗?
Can they not wait?
你们就不能等等吗?!
Can you not wait?!
她亲见他被折磨和杀害
She watched him being tortured and killed,
目睹了全程
moment by moment.
他已经死了
He's dead.
但我们没有
But we are not.
我们的亲人在加利利北部等我们回归
Our flesh and blood waits up north in Galilee for our return.
我们现在要为家人着想
Our duty now is to our families.
三天
Three days.
这是我欠他的
I owe him that much.
我们对他的信仰值得等这三天
Our faith in him has to be worth three days.
要是他第三日没有复活呢?
And if he fails to rise on the third?
那我们像男人一样离开
Then we leave like men.
而不是懦夫
Not cowards.
你认为他会回来
You think he's coming back.
我相信他会
I know he is.
你怎能如此确定?
How are you so sure?
他让别人重生过
He raised others from death.
预言如是说
This is what was prophesied.
而且他保证过
And he promised.
所以何不复活自己呢?
Then why not himself?
- 大祭司  - 啊
- High priest.  - Ah.
我要你在亚利马太的坟墓布下寺庙的守卫
I want you to post temple guards at Arimathea's tomb.
必须封死墓穴
It must remain sealed.
守卫不许跟任何人说话 不许让任何人通过
They speak to no one, they let no one pass,
而且他们只听命于我
and they report only to me.
找到加略人了
Iscariot's been found.
那个叛徒?
The betrayer?
他能带我们找到其他人吗?
Well, will he lead us to the others?
他死在了波特墓园
He lies dead in the Potter's field.
上吊自尽
He hanged himself.
这个耶稣到底有什么本领
What is it about this Jesus
让他们如此疯狂?
that drives them to such madness?
有何关系呢?
What does it matter?
没有尸体 他们就不能假装他起死复生
Without his body, they can't pretend he's risen from death.
你陪他到最后一刻了吗?
You were with him at the end?
只有约翰
Only John.
罗马人杀害他的场景极其残忍
The Romans turned his death into an atrocious spectacle.
他们把他打到皮开肉绽
They flayed him until his back split open.
就好像想把他的肉一片一片地割下来
It was as if they wanted to cut him down one piece at a time
直到他不能动弹
until he could barely move.
他们逼他跪下 把荆棘插进他的头里
They forced him to his feet and drove thorns into his head.
他们逼着他...
They made him...
拖着十字架走到各各它
drag his cross to Golgotha,
把他钉在了上面...
where they nailed him to it...
然后竖起来示众
and raised him up for all to see.
你不在并没有关系
It doesn't matter that you weren't there.
他理解我们的软弱
He understood our weakness.
他爱我们如此
He loved us for it.
为此而死
Died for it.
如今这都不重要了
None of this matters now.
你听到狂热者的话了
You heard the zealot.
我们得在被他们找到之前离开
We need to leave before they find us.
在轮到我们钉在十字架上之前
Before it's our turn to look down from Golgotha.
你得休息了
You need to rest.
这段时期非常紧张
It's been a stressful period.
而你在安抚民众上
You've done exceptionally well
做得非常出色
to steer the community to calmer waters.
离不开你一如既往的支持
With your support, as ever.
你很好地利用了彼拉多来保护我们
You've used Pilate to great effect to protect us.
来睡觉吧
Come to bed.
我马上就好
I won't be long.
他犯了亵渎神明之罪
The charge is blasphemy.
应当处死!
He deserves to die!
真理?
Truth?
何为真理?
What is truth?
我不认识他!
I don't know him!
你们认错人了!
You're mistaken!
我没见过他!
I've never seen him before!
罗马封条被打破了
The Roman seal has been broken.
墓地门户大开 拿撒勒人...
The tomb is now opened and the Nazarene...
不见了
is gone.
"不见了"是什么意思?
What do you mean "gone"?
拿撒勒人...
The Nazarene...
不见了
is gone.
"不见了"是什么意思?
What do you mean "gone"?
你相信他是死而复生吗?
Do you believe he's risen from the dead?
这是他保证会发生的事
This is what he promised would happen.
我们不能眼睁睁看着兄弟姐妹受苦
We cannot watch as our brothers and sisters suffer.
宣扬他的教义
Spread his word.
神的国度将要降临
The Kingdom of God is coming.
我必须想个办法阻止他们
I have to find a way to stop them.
我以此全权委托于你 必要的话 可以不择手段
This gives you my full authority. Do whatever is necessary.
时机已成熟
The time has come.
谢谢你杀光了他们
Thanks to kill them all.
您在此 我们信仰您
You are there to believe.
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调&校对: 影子
翻译: 奥利奥 飘飘行天下 鸟生鱼汤 舒大卷子 波特妹子